Guide to the Frederick W. M. Holliday papers, 1846-1899 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Frederick W. M. Holliday papers 1846-1899 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Holliday, Fred. W. M. (Frederick William Mackey), 1828-1899.
3.0 linear feet Extent: 2,194 Items
Lawyer, and Governor of Virginia, from Winchester (Frederick Co.), Virginia. Papers contain letters from Holliday while a student at Yale University, 1846; papers relating to the 33rd Virginia Regiment, which Holliday raised and commanded during the Civil War; letters concerning the International Exhibition held in Philadelphia in 1876, at which Holliday served as a commissioner from Virginia; and letters and papers relating to Holliday's election as governor in 1877; and letters from his term as governor, for the most part dealing with routine political and administrative matters. Also includes printed matter and scrapbooks of clippings and letter books created while Holliday was a student at Yale and at the University of Virginia, 1845-1849, and as governor of Virginia, 1878-1879; and four record books concerning Holliday's legal work.
RL.00586
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Provenance
The Frederick W. M. Holliday Papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from 1936-1955.
Biographical Note
Frederick William Mackey Holliday, of Winchester (Frederick Co.), Va., was a member of the Confederate Congress and the 38th Governor of Virginia from 1878 to 1882.
Collection Overview
The papers of Frederick William Mackey Holliday contain letters from Holliday while a student at Yale University, 1846; papers relating to the 33rd Virginia Regiment, which Holliday raised and commanded during the Civil War; letters concerning the International Exhibition held in Philadelphia in 1876, at which Holliday served as a commissioner from Virginia; and letters and papers relating to Holliday's election as governor of Virginia in 1877 and letters from his term as governor, for the most part dealing with routine political and administrative matters.
Printed material includes The Struggles, Perils and Hopes of the Negroes in the United States, a pamphlet by Reverend C. Clifton Penick, 1893; a typed copy of The Virginia Debt in Politics, by William L. Royall, published in 1897 as History of the Virginia debt controversy; and broadsides, campaign literature, and other political material.
Volumes include ten scrapbooks of clippings; letter books of Holliday as a student at Yale and the University of Virginia, 1845-1849, and as governor of Virginia, 1878-1879; and four record books concerning Holliday's legal work.
Subject Headings
Holliday, Fred. W. M. (Frederick William Mackey), 1828-1899; Confederate States of America. Army. Virginia Infantry Regiment, 33rd; University of Virginia -- Students; Yale University -- Students; African Americans -- United States; Centennial Exhibition (1876: Philadelphia, Pa.); College students -- United States -- Correspondence; Lawyers -- Correspondence; Lawyers -- Virginia -- Winchester; Universities and colleges -- United States -- History; Governors -- Virginia; Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Virginia -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; Scrapbooks
Contents of Collection
- Frederick W. M. Holliday papers, 1846-1899 and undated, (8 boxes)
  - Manuscript Papers, 1846-1899 and undated, bulk 1862-1895
    - 1846-1877, July (Box 1)
    - 1877, August-1879 October (Box 2)
    - 1879, November-1886 (Box 3)
    - 1887-1894, March (Box 4)
    - 1894, April-1899 (Box 5)
    - Undated papers (Box 6)
    - Printed materials (Box 6)
    - Bound volumes (Box 7-8)
  - Other Bound Volumes
    - Account book, 1867-1869 (Volume M:5945)
      Record of charges for legal work.
    - Account book, 1867-1877 (Volume M:5946)
    - Account book, 1870-1880 (Volume M:5948)
      Record of legal work.
    - Letter book, 1845-1847 (Volume L:5349)
      New Haven, Connecticut.
    - Letter book, 1847-1849 (Volume F:5350)
      New Haven, Connecticut and Virginia.
    - Letter book, 1878-1879 (Volume F:5351)
      Richmond, Virginia.
    - Scrapbook, 1850-1899 (Volume M:5352)
      Contains clippings, addresses, bills, etc. Explanatory notes are in Holliday's handwritting.
    - Account book, 1869-1877 (Volume F:5947)
    - Account book, 1873-1886 (Volume F:5949)